[Music]
Heat. Heat.
Heat up here.
Hello, good evening, good day everybody
and welcome to the latest episode of the
Ask a Bijit Show. I hope everybody is
doing great. Let me see who all is there
on the live chat. By the way, today is
not a super chat session. We I'm going
to take just questions from the live
chat for a change because people have
been saying that. So why not go back to
this for one episode. Yes. So today it's
all going to be live chat. No super
chat. I've switched off super chat.
Let's see who all is there on the live
stream. I can see Samrat Shukla Mystic
SK Dashan Patil Shashank Koshik Aditya
Gaquad Abijit Tripati 2K Watts
Photography Vishal Patro Xenomorphosis
UC Anonymous Scientist Rishies Das Gupta
Yashwant Sudir Prakash Bhya Hunter
Canway Liat Vidi Manar Dungar Singh
Johan Brides SK Mr. Manic Sumesh Kota
Shri Chandraaya Namaha Rahul Lakshmanan
Utkash Rao Duv Durya Pratam Sharma
Geopolitical Dubai Rashmi Ratur
Truthful Penguin DGBHF
Aush Singh Dashan Patel Tanesh Pande
Push Rana Sentin SP Galler Priyanchi Sud
Aditya Singh Anand Chandak Prren Paul
from Kolkata Love Achara Mystic SK Sum
Kota Ironclad Ad Axit Sahil Om Gro Vha
Suas Ready Aradhya Dashore Abijit Chabra
Light
Ankad Zone Ichino Senpai Kaizen 007 sent
in SP Nishal
Ry uh Spade Pratam Sharma and everybody
everybody everybody else thank you so
much for being on the live stream
instead of just greeting you all let's
take some questions so please go ahead
please ask your questions I'll take as
many as possible. Uh Mlevin says I can
see some more people. Hers Janvi Pratam
and so on so forth. Okay. Mlevin says
apparently Air India serviced their
planes from a Turkish company. They had
decided to replace them after the India
Pakistan conflict but this it seems like
like this plane was serviced by them. I
think I think we're going to have to
wait for the investigation to happen.
Wait for the the the the facts to come
out. Maybe this is one of the facts
that's coming out. I'm not sure. Um
yeah. So, so let's let's wait and watch.
It's been a terrible terrible tragedy.
Um the aircraft just trying to take off
and goes to a certain height and then
just loses power both engines. Crazy.
So, yeah. Okay. So, let's see if this
turns out to be, you know, um verifiable
information. Let's see.
Um anonymous scientist says was the
fight between Donald Trump and Elon Musk
pre-planned? There is always the
possibility that that something like
this may be pre-planned. Yeah. But uh
asking me that question means you you're
expecting that maybe I have uh knowledge
that is restricted and and secret. So I
don't have that knowledge. There's
always a possibility that you know you
may stage a flight a fight. You stage a
fight a fake fight to see who who stands
with whom and so on. That way you can
make out who are your true friends and
your true enemies and that helps you in
many ways. So it's possible but we don't
know for sure.
Ankan Zhon says what do you think? How
did the Ahmedabad air crash tragedy
happen? It's too early to say. It looks
like both the engines failed
because because you can see the the
aircraft take off. It's going fine and
suddenly you can see it lose power. and
it's still flaring like that. It just
flares all the way down and crashes. So,
it looks like both engines lost power
simultaneously. Now, the real question
is why did that happen? And that that we
have to see. I don't I don't know for
sure. Um it's extremely rare like I like
I said during my brief presentation
about such incidents. Extremely rare for
such a thing to happen. Simultaneous
dual engine um failure. Incredibly rare.
So generally it happens when you the
plane ingests volcanic ash right um but
there's no volcanic ash here it happens
when there's icing of the system the the
fuel system but there's no ice in ADA I
assure you of that and it could happen
if there's a massive bilateral bird
strike and that now that's a possibility
we have to look into u I'm not really
familiar with Ahmedabad airport I'm
familiar with some of the airports so do
you have flocks of bird around the
Ahmedabad airport. If if you have flocks
of bird birds then this could have
contributed possibly but we'll have to
see. We'll have to see. It's too early
to say.
Okay. Dashan Patil says just out of E5.
Loved it. Thank you so much. We had all
believed that Trump government would
benefit India more than more but Trump
is in favor of Pakistan more than ever.
Operation Sudindu should have continued.
It will hurt us always. these problems
occur, they they pop up. You know, the
US has
a long-standing tradition of supporting
and favoring Pakistan and Trump is
simply the latest example of that. And
uh you see Pakistan is a very attractive
nation for people who are plunder
oriented because the Pakistani um
because the Pakistani dictatorship is
perfectly okay with having foreigners
plunder their land and their resources
and their people. Right? So that's
that's something Pakistan has that India
doesn't. We have way more resources but
we are not open to someone like Trump
coming and plundering our resources. we
are okay with him
you know investing in the extraction of
resources provided that he does it he
does so properly and it's a win-win
situation rather than a Trump 10 India 1
situation but when it comes to Pakistan
Pakistan is okay with Trump 100 Pakistan
2 so you see that that's that that's why
Pakistan always uh succeeds when it
comes to these predatory nations so yeah
that's where we
Uh Aush Singh says our hard power score
must have changed. Uh not quite not
quite. Hard power score from my the way
I calculated it doesn't change every 15
15 days 20 days every 2 months. It
depends on very simple factors that are
publicly available data. It depends on
your land area, your population. Okay,
that that's that going to change. It
depends on your military budget. It
depends on GDP. These are rising. So
actually your hard power is rising. It
depends on your power projection capabil
capabilities. It depends on your nuclear
power. Everything is rising. So our hard
power is not is not changing because of
that. The only thing that can decrease
our large power is the sovereignty
score. If our sovereignty score drops
below one, I'm not sure if it has
dropped below one despite everything
that's happened recently. So we still
have five nations with a sovereignty
score of one. That's the US, China,
India, Pakist, India, Russia and Israel.
So a so based on all these factors, our
hard power score has actually probably
increased since the last time I
calculated it.
Okay. Um
Rohan says uh first of all heartfelt
condolences to the people who died in
the unfort unfortunate plane crash. I
agree. Yeah. Uh do you think the attack
on the Indian embassy in US and UK are
inter in intentionally enabled? I mean
which attacks on there's nothing
recently that's happened as far as I
know but in the past you've had attacks
on the Indian embassy embassy and
consulates in the UK. Uh I'm not sure
about the US but you had such incidents
in Canada as well. Are these
intentionally enabled? Yes, they are
intentionally enabled.
Yes, they are
because it's very easy for you to block
any protests and any attacks on a
foreign embassy. We have foreign
embassies all over the place in a
certain part of Delhi. Okay, the place
called Chanakipuri. We have embassies
all over the place and that's a very
well patrolled area. You have a lot of
security measures in place over there
and it's it's it's not like you can just
walk in there and start protesting
against an embassy unless the government
is okay with it. Similarly, other
governments like in places in cities
like London or wherever you have Ottawa
etc. uh Washington DC the local
governments can very much prevent
protesters from coming anywhere near a
specific embassy if they want but if
they are okay with this happening then
they then you can have attacks that
happen. So
um
Jason Dy says why was Aim Moner invited
to the White House? Does this indicate
hostility for India? In case you just
witnessed my previous live stream which
happened like 60 seconds ago
uh geio strategy episode 5. If you watch
the second part of that the second
segment you will understand exactly why
Aim Munir was invited to the white
house. He's deeply involved in Trump
business operations.
Okay. Which are benefiting the Trump
family. The Trump family,
they they they see a value of about $65
trillion in Pakistan
and they would love to exploit that and
Aim Mun would love to have them exploit
everything and take everything out of
Pakistan as long as he gets some
benefits. So, it's a win-win for Aim
Munir and and the Trump family. But I'm
not sure if it's a win for Pakistan. I
don't know if it's a win for the US.
Maybe it's a win for the US and so on.
So does this indicate hostility for
India? Well, it it indicates this great
love for Pakistan and Asim Mun which
naturally means a level of hostility for
India. There you have it. Yes, it does.
Okay. Um
geopolitical dub says Guyana sized oil
discovery likely in Andaman sea stated
by minister Hardipuri. Do we have such
oil reserves to be the become a net
exporter?
If you put money in explore exploration
if we yeah explore this seriously well
if you have a Guyana sized resources I
think we can become a net exporter. I
think our energy resources are
criminally under uh explored.
I think we if we properly re you know do
do an exploration of all the undersea
oil and and gas resources that we have
of the western eastern etc coasts of
India the Anderman region the laxadep
region the so-called Arabian sea region
which is a sea of subashtra etc. I think
if we do this properly and if we look at
the ter terrestrial resources that we
have and if we do this properly I think
we could possibly become the greatest
exporter of energy. Yeah. So u I'm glad
to hear that there's a possible Guyana
sized oil discovery in the Andaman Sea.
I haven't heard of it thus far. Let's
let's quickly take a look at it. Let me
try and Google it. I haven't seen this
this news this far. Um stay signed out.
Oil discovery
discovery and the man and man no
discovery
exclusive interview with the with new
Indian so and so minister Mr. Hadib
Simuri laid at D hinting that the
country may be on the cusp of
discovering a game-changing oil reserve.
India on the brink of a 20 trillion
leap. Guyana sized oil discovery likely.
I don't care about likely. Is it
discovered or not?
Uh, okay. So, this doesn't really answer
my question. He's saying something may
be likely. Well, I am I've been saying
it for a long time. So, things are
likely, but but where is it? You should
talk about these things only after you
actually discover something. So, I don't
know about this, but I think you know
should be able to find stuff pretty
soon. So, there we have it.
Um
okay now what else? Uh Shubam says does
India need to have long-term plans to
weaken down US and Chinese economies?
Look whatever plans we have we will not
discuss and we will not discuss them
openly and uh I'm sure look the US is
not not a friend of ours. It's very very
clear by now. US is acting like an enemy
of ours. They're siding with our enemies
and uh so on. I mean there have so many
projects that are going on that are uh
that are
that are bad for India in for Indian
national interests for Indian
geopolitical interests. Um they are
actively trying to harm Indian interests
in a variety of ways. A variety of ways.
Uh whether it's the US or whether it's
the Chinese both of them. So we should
always have plans to take counter
measures is what I would say.
S of Pandis Kumar Pandit says, "Can this
be a fuel sabotage? There is
contamination of fuel." Watch my
previous live stream episode 5 in which
I've gone into the possible causes of a
simultaneous dual engine failure in
which you can have u fuel contamination
as a as a factor right now. Fuel
sabotage and all I will not not go into
all these speculative theories at this
point in time. It's too early. Let the
government do a proper investigation and
let them announce what has happened.
I will not go into speculation at this
point in time.
Right.
Uh Brides SK says, "Time is ticking. Do
you think Israel will will risk
attacking Iran's nuclear facilities
which Israel has vowed to never allow?
Iran warned to strike back Israel,
demonuclear sites and so on.
We'll see. I don't know what what
Israel's calculations are. Uh obviously
time is ticking. Time is ticking. You
are right. Like you say, you must have
watched some of my previous episodes of
Geost Strategy. I did say there's a
significant chance, non-trivial chance
of uh the whole matter coming to a
becoming a flash point. And why is why
do I say the clock is ticking? Why do I
say this is a increasingly dangerous
flash point? It's because Iran is said
to have enough file material, nuclear
file material for about 10 nuclear
warheads by now. And they have
significant reserves now of uranium that
has been enriched to in excess of 60%
maybe more. And the enrichment is going
on and the nuclear talks are not going
anywhere. The Americans are making
maximalist demands and the Iranians are
would one would say rightfully from
their perspective rejecting these
demands.
as a sovereign nation. So it looks like
there's no headway and the Iranians are
continuing to enrich uranium which is a
matter of huge concern for Israel
because Israel is is a regional nation.
It's a nation in the neighborhood of of
Iran. Now there's a there's a distance
of about a thousand kilometers roughly
between the borders of Iran and Israel.
There's another nation in between which
is uh Iraq. Obviously there's Jordan as
well and so on. But you know Yeah. So
the longer time goes, the more file
material the Iranians will have that
could potentially be used in nuclear
weapons. So Iran, Israel would love to
end this nuclear program once and for
all, but Iran has significant u you know
offensive capabilities.
Um they have excellent missiles, very
large quantities of missiles and so on.
So, it's a risk that Iran that that
Israel takes on if it decides to attack
is Iranian nuclear facilities. It does
take on a big risk if it does that
because yeah, Dimona. So, Dimona is is a
nuclear it's a nuclear site. I can show
you where it is. It's not very hard to
find. I have shown it before in the
pasta on on various previous live
streams. So, let's quickly take a look
at it. Beer Shiva.
So let's go to Israel. Let's go to the
satellite imagery.
And it is near the city of Beer Shiva.
Uh the Dimuna. Here is Dimona. And it's
not at Dimona, but it's outside of
Dimuna that we have this nuclear
facility.
And uh yep, here we have it. This I
think this is the one we're talking
about. Are we? Uh let us see. Let us
see. This is a chemical
thing. This is a chemical plant. Okay,
one second. Where was it? I have to zoom
out a little bit more.
And yeah, NEGV. Here it is. NEGV. The
NEGV nuclear research center.
And here we have the the the reactors
and so on. So,
I'm sure it's very well defended, but
you know, hitting a target with
ballistic or cruise missiles is just a
mathematical thing. All you have to do
is to saturate the strike zone with more
missiles than the defense system can
handle. It's as simple as that. It's a
mathematical thing. So, if uh Iran can
do that, well, it it'll end up hitting
the Mona. But yeah, hitting a nuclear
power plant, a nuclear weapons uh
production plant, it's a very dangerous
thing to do because then it invites very
harsh responses and so on. So it depends
on what Israel first does and then Iran
may respond in a certain way.
Okay. Pranay Paul says, "With pro- Hamas
rallies and mob mob violence now now
routine in LA, is this free speech or
just chaos disguised as democracy?"
Uh well it's actually surprising that
these things are happening in the US.
The US is a police state. They don't
allow
um historically traditionally they have
not been very lenient when it comes to
demonstrations against state power. I
mean what happened during the Vietnam
war protests in various universities
students were shot
um
and so on. So what does this tell you?
these pro- Hamas rallies, it looks like
there's a political dimension to this.
These are it looks like these are um
these are politically motivated
protests. So, see that the the
Republicans, they are anti-immigration,
they are anti-Hamas, they are pro-Israel
and so on. And they are pro pro- orderer
and the Democrats are a leftist party.
So, they are pro- Hamas, they are pro-
immigration, they are pro- anarchy and
all that. So it looks like maybe
possibly I'm not saying there's any
proof, but I'm saying possibly it it's
possible that perhaps the Democrats may
be behind this. So this could be a
political challenge to the Trump
administration and uh California is a
state ruled by Democrats. So that makes
it easier to do that, right? And then
that brings the governor of California
in a direct clash with the president of
the US. So is this free speech, is this
chaos? I think it's neither free speech
it's nor neither is it chaos it's it's a
political movement it's a political
thing that's happening
her says is Mayad current king Laksha
Singh Mayar puppet king or real king
there are no real kings in India what
what what country are you living in
there are no real kings in India what is
a real king it's a king who has power
a king who has a title I am a king but
who has no power is not a king
being A king means having the power of a
king.
But inheriting some title from
somewhere, it doesn't mean you're a
king. It just means you have a title. So
there are no kings today in India.
That's the that's my answer to you. I
hope you understand it.
Uh
I don't know.
I have to I have to hunt for good
questions.
Uh Sri Raachendra Nama says do bricks
really matter? Bricks does matter to a
certain extent but the problem with
bricks is that it's an economic kind of
uh coalition of nations. Uh it's not a
military alliance of any kind or or even
any economic alliance of any kind. Uh
which means that you know you don't have
any proper leadership a strong
leadership. You obviously have a a
strong nation that kind of wants to use
bricks for its own purposes for its own
agenda which makes it unlikely that the
other nations will contribute much to
it. So you have China who wants to use
bricks as as an instrument for
strengthening China's
geopolitical agenda. But obviously India
will not participate in that. So when
you have a major nation like India
that's not really a big participant in
bricks then bricks becomes kind of a
lame duck thing. Even Russia sees China
as an adversary. I have been saying that
for a very long time. Now the New York
Times agrees with me.
So when you have two nations Russia and
India that look upon China as an
adversary but would like to benefit from
whatever overall advantages you perhaps
someday may get out of a economic
coalition that's why you are in it. So
it doesn't really matter overall. It
really cannot change things the way the
EU which is an official alliance can do.
So bricks at this point in time doesn't
really matter a very a lot.
Okay.
Veov says why shouldn't Iran develop
nuclear weapons? Isn't this the same
case as the US getting buttth hurt by
India's nuclear testing? Well if you are
the big power with the big nukes then
you don't want anybody to become a
potential challenger today. you will be
small but in 20 years you'll be bigger
and then it may be a problem. So that's
why the US doesn't want any new
challenges to arise. And that's why they
are telling Iran, I don't care if you're
sovereign or not. I you don't have the
right to nuclear weapons. And Iran is
saying, go take a hike. Take a hike. I
am a sovereign nation. I'll do what I
want. So my answer is Iran has every
right to do whatever everybody else can
do.
If the US can have nuclear weapons, if
China can have it, if India can have it,
Russia can have it. Even if if even
Pakistan can have nuclear weapons, why
can't Iran have nuclear weapons?
Excuse me. So from a sovereignty
perspective, Iran has the right to do
whatever it wants. Um other nations may
see it as a threat. Well, it's that
that's that is their problem. Uh so
yeah, that's the deal.
Uh
NTN888 says you said India should
develop its own Starlink for security
reasons. Not just security reasons, for
financial reasons also. You can get a
lot of money from the world if you have
a good service to offer. So this lead to
vast inefficient and duplication. What
is Starling necessary? Instead develop
better develop suitable terrestrial tech
like 5G. Starlink is a geostrategic
project.
It has a dual purpose. The first purpose
is to make a raise a lot of money for
Elon Musk with which he will build his
Mars rockets and all that. Okay. So you
offer these internet services across the
world. sitting at home or sitting in a
forest or sitting on top of Mount
Everest, you can get, you know, 10 Mbps
internet. Well, that's great, right?
That's great. Uh, so that that's the
sort of thing he's offering. No matter
where you are, you will have access. So,
I am sure and it's it's pretty expensive
internet, but I suppose people some
people will want to buy it. And of
course, if you are going to Antarctica,
if you're going in the middle for for a
for a hike in the middle of forest,
etc., this could be useful.
And so on so forth. So there are various
reasons why people would want to buy it.
So he's offering that and with that he
hopes to raise money a lot of money
hopefully. So he's putting up a
constellation of thousands of satellites
all across uh all across earth orbit low
earth orbit right that's one reason why
starink exists to provide the service
and make money for Elon Musk. The other
reason is a hidden reason. I'm pretty
sure it has spying capabilities on the
rest of the world. I'm sure it is spy
cap cameras and other whatever it is
it's capable of of providing 24 by7
coverage of the surface of the planet
and that's a very powerful asset if it
is the case for the US government.
So that's why Starling exists. It's it's
it's a vital geopolitical asset for the
US.
Now from a civilian perspective, okay,
it's a very huge waste of money. Why not
just have a terrestrial network like 5G,
etc. But but as a nation, you don't
think that way. As a civilian, you will
think that way. But as a nation, you
want global surveillance if you're a
superpower. So you will invest in that.
Okay? So it's different the way
civilians think and it's different the
way large nations think and powerful
nations think. For them, these these
investments are worth worth the price.
Now I said that we are a rising nation,
a growing nation. We have security
challenges. So we need to to ideally
have our own Starlink like constellation
vast inefficiency, duplication, that's a
civilian perspective. I'm talking about
national security perspective in which
in from that perspective whether it's
duplication etc blah blah blah blah blah
blah it's all worth it. Okay.
Right.
Uh, Prome says, "How can satellites
affect Earth if there is millions of
them orbiting 100 men versus one gorilla
type thing?" The satellites will be made
from materials that were extracted out
of the Earth.
So the satellite if there's a million
satellites, it's a significant amount of
mass, but the mass came from the Earth
itself. So it's not going to have a
significant impact on the earth because
it's going to be an extension of the
earth's mass and the these little tiny
little satellites compared to the earth
they cannot really exert any massive
grow gravitational pool or anything
significant
uh whatever it's going to be it's going
to be a negligible impact. So it's not
going to change uh the the the it's not
going to affect tides let's say or
something like that you know so it
doesn't really end up affecting the
earth in any significant
way.
Rishab says what's your choice whether
there should be war between Iran and the
US or Israel is it good for India?
What's good for India is that the
current geopolitical balance of power in
the region continues. Let's take a look
at the map. What's the geopolitical
balance of power like in the region?
Uh where is map? Here is map. Where is
the map? Here is map. So we're talking
about this region, the extended
subcontinent region. We're going
westwards which is into West Asia. So
over here the balance of power is that
the major most powerful nation is India.
In westwards we have a terrorist nation
Pakistan. We have Afghanistan which
wants to be left alone. Don't bother me.
That's it. That's all it wants. There's
the central Asian nations that are part
of the Russian geopolitical sphere of
influence. Then there's Iran which wants
to become more powerful. There's Saudi
Arabia which is a US ally. There's Oman,
UAE, etc. All the all these nations here
are in various ways US allies. There's
Yemen which is an Iranian ally and so
on. And then there is Israel which is
America's number one ally. So and then
there is Iraq which is now a non- entity
because the Americans destroyed Iraq in
2003 and ever since Iraq has been has
become a nation that is under US
occupation. It is a non- entity now. It
has no geopolitical power of its own. So
the Americans completely transformed the
balance of power in the region in the
year 2003. Now they would like this to
happen once again with by taking out
Iran which would make the region very
strongly pro- US and the US becomes a
very powerful nation in the region more
than it currently is indirectly.
So what is best for India? You know
Indians love Israel etc. and Israel is a
very good uh partner of India in
technology and and various other things.
But what's good for India is that Iran
continues to exist the way it way it is
right now. Even an Iran that rises would
be overall good for India as long as it
doesn't become as powerful as India and
in which case there could be a conflict
of some kind. But uh I would very much
like to see Iran continue to exist. I
don't want it to be destroyed. I don't
want it it to suffer a revolution or
some kind of transition to democracy or
whatever. Iran's political system and
political model is is their internal
matter. Okay? We we have no business
interfering in that. So let Iran exist
the way it does. If Iran is destroyed,
it will create a huge hole, geopolitical
hole in the region which will lead to an
imbalance of power and then something
will rush in and fill the vacuum. That
will be geopolitical instability. It
will go in a direction that's not good
for India. So my choice is there should
be no war between Iran and the US
because if there's a war, Iran will put
up a big fight, but Iran will lose
because the US is just too powerful. And
the same goes with Israel. If Israel and
Iran go to war, the Americans will come
to Israel's aid guaranteed.
So yeah, that's that's the deal. Um
I from my perspective, Iran should
continue to exist the way it does. It
should nothing should change over here.
Uh Sumit Garbal says recently Tucker
Carl Carlson said that the deep state
should weaken India. These fellows okay
I'm not aware whether it's true or not.
I've not seen the quote or whatever. But
these fellows think they can play God
with the world.
So they will think that way because they
are all powerful. Their country is all
powerful. The response to that is that
we should keep our heads down. Stop
boasting and bragging about Vishwaguru
and uh uh superpower and all that
nonsense.
Put your heads down and get to work.
Work as hard as possible the next 20
years. Then we'll put our head up and
see where we are now. That's it.
Rohan Suna says why is it that Sweden
having only a defense budget of $13
billion and India 86 billion. We don't
have our own cutting edge equipment but
Sweden has. Look at Visby class
corvette. Look at the Gothink class
Goautling class submarines,
right? What is it called? Goautling.
Goautling class
submarine. Goautand Gautland class
submarine. It costs $100 million a
piece. Peanuts. Well, it can take down
aircraft carriers. Go land class
submarines. So why is it so is the
question. We have a defense budget of
900 what? $86 billion. Sweden is $13
billion but they manufacture their own
things. It's because they have a
long-standing tradition of manufacturing
their own things. And we in our case the
government never allowed this until the
past in the past 10 years. Now we have
this focus on developing our own defense
equipment. Wait 10 years we're going to
be a different beast.
All you need is to unleash unleash the
the the talent and creativity of the
Indian people and the and the
industriousness of the Indian people. So
once this is unleashed by the government
of India, we're going to change very
rapidly. So in another 10 years we're
going to be a major defense exporter and
things will be different. We we're going
to have various kinds of various
different kinds of aircraft, different
kinds of helicopters, different kinds of
howitzers and artillery and machine guns
and whatnot and uh warships and
submarines and offensive and defensive
equipment of various kinds and so on. So
the moment you allow a nation to develop
its own industries industries then then
this is what you have. So Sweden has a
long tradition of of having these niche
industries that they excel in in the
military domain. So that's why they have
the situation.
Right. Okay.
Um,
Yashwan says, "Should the government of
India consider removing access to IAEA
after crossing a third certain threshold
as an economic power? Considering
increased deaths of Indian nuclear
scientists after giving them access
after giving access to IAEA." Okay. I
have heard I keep hearing about these
deaths of Indian nuclear scientists. So
maybe it must be real thing. I've never
gone and looked into the details. My
point is giving IA access to Indian
nuclear facilities is is tantamount to
foreign interference. But maybe we have
we have signed some agreements which
require us to do that. I am sure just
like we've walked away from the Indust
treaty because it was not good for us.
Similarly in the future when we are
powerful enough we can walk away from
these various agreements. The moment it
makes sense for us to walk away from
them. Right now we are not that
powerful. So let's let's currently be in
that. I I agree that this is not a good
thing for India. Who the hell is the
IAEA to come and inspect our facilities?
It's kind of humiliating. But we signed
some agreements with very powerful
nations which is why we have to do this
for the time being. Eventually we'll
throw them out. Absolutely. We should
throw them out each and every one of
them.
White Fang was a dog. Wolf. Okay. White
Fang. Some people are speculating that
things happening in the US indicate the
beginning of the down of the downfall of
a civilization that's already passed its
peak. What's your view on this? So the
US is not a civilization. The West is
not a civilization.
It's an empire. The US is an empire. In
Western civilization,
it's not a civilization. Okay? The West
is not one entity. It's a lots of
different entities that have been
subsumed forcibly into one thing and
that's why they claim there's a western
civilization. There's no such thing.
There used to be a Slavic civilization.
There used to be well there was
Indo-Uropean culture all over the place
and it manifested itself in various
different forms like the Slavic
civilization, like the Anglo-Saxon
culture, like the um like the Celtic
culture and so on and so forth. But you
you take all these things together and
smash them together and say it's one
civilization. That's a lie. It's a cope
because they have no no civilization of
their own. Even Rome wasn't a
civilization. It was an empire. Greece
was a civilization that no longer
exists. It's been destroyed by
Christianity
and the old Indo-Uropean culture has
been destroyed by Christianity. Now
that's the preface to what I have to
answer.
So things are happening in the US which
indicates the downfall the beginning
beginning of the downfall of the US
civilization. First of all the US
doesn't have a civilization. It's just
an empire. It doesn't really have a
culture of its own. Yeah. Now you could
say it has some kind of culture. Yeah.
Guns is a culture. Drinking beer
underage is is their culture and so on
so forth. So on so forth. promiscuity
and um and and and single parenthood is
their culture, right? A person having
like 15 different sexual partners at the
same time is culture and so on. So
that's not the elements the the elements
of a civilization. That's not the
characteristic of of a civilization. But
it wasn't always like this. The US was
very different in the 1950s. It wasn't
like this. It had much higher standards
at that time. time in the 1950s it had
the high it had the highest standards
anywhere in the world and then things
things started slipping slowly
imperceptibly
gradually but then it it ends up with
today where things are like night and
day difference between the US of now and
the US of the 1950s very different so
there is a decline in cultural standards
in the US no question it's very visible
but I don't consider the has to be a
civilization.
But the decline of the moral fabric of
society is very visible. So yeah, it's
it's it's a society that's in decline.
It's a society that's deca decaying,
but as a power, it's at the pinnacle of
its power. So imagine a society that is
that has no moral standards, that has
very low moral values or an absence of
values and they are the most powerful
nation. I mean, imagine that's that's
that's a nightmare scenario. That's my
view on this that a nation with no
ethical moral standards is lecturing the
world on all kinds of random things and
it has the most powerful military in the
world and they have a nuclear doctrine
that says that before the US for
whatever reason gets destroyed, it
should destroy all the the entire world.
So if if if
let's say the US is on the verge of
losing nuclear war to Russia, then it's
required to nuke every country in the
world, it's required to nuke India. Why?
Because that's the doctrine. I mean, how
evil is that? How evil is that? Yes.
Okay.
Uh Dashian Patel says you are not in
favor of AC carriers.
I I think I understand what you're
trying to say here. Aircraft carriers.
Aircraft carriers I think you are
saying. Yes. Okay. But with the air
defense capabilities shown during
operation Synindor would your opinion
change a bit? No.
We need subaria. We need the most
dangerous things available and the most
dangerous thing and scary thing is what
cannot be seen but which has which has a
tremendous amount of firepower.
Now it's it's an aircraft carrier is a
luxury that a superpower can afford
but and and and I'm sure an aircraft
carrier will be valuable against
Pakistan for example.
Pakistan um doesn't have the bo best
offensive capabilities and we have some
of the best defensive missiles in the
world. So we have missiles that will
serve as point defense for warships and
aircraft carriers. So I'm sure we can
pretty much safeguard an aircraft
carrier properly. But what if we we have
to for example hypothetically fight the
Americans?
The aircraft carrier will be a sitting
duck in that case or let's say fight the
Pak fight the Chinese. The Chinese
warships have VLS tubes with what 128
plus missiles,
offensive missiles. You have two, three
warships. It's it numerically it
numerically overwhelms you and then you
lose your most precious asset. So I
think my opinion hasn't changed one bit.
Operation Synindhur was against a weak
nation.
So that doesn't really matter. So my
opinion hasn't changed. I think aircraft
carriers are not required for a nation
like India at this point in time. In 20
years when we are let's say 1520
trillion dollar economy yeah sure in
that in at that time we should have
aircraft carriers. So the two that we
have today two or whatever number we
have today keep them. I'm not saying get
rid of them. Keep them
and in the future maybe they will be of
some use but right now we need
submarines. That's the most important
thing.
Okay. A 2K watts photography says Russia
has offered Sikoy 57 export version with
its source code under make in India.
What retaliation could we expect from
the US if we get this aircraft by the
time AMC is mass-produced? The Americans
will impose some kind of sanctions on
India or they will throw some kind of
tantrum or they will further you know
arm the Pakistanis or something. The
Americans will throw some kind of
tantrum and try to harm India in
multiple ways.
But they expect India to be a vas and we
will not be a vas. They expect us to buy
the flying trash can which is the F-35.
We're not going to buy that. There are
various Indian
analysts who are uh shilling for the US
and who are u who are saying who are
recommending that we buy the F-35. My
opinion is very clear. The F-35 is a
piece of flying flying piece of garbage.
I don't know how good or bad the SG57
is. I think it's a I'm sure it's a
decent aircraft.
I maybe it has some defects and
deficiencies perhaps, but so does the
F-35. The F-35 comes with poison.
The Sukoy doesn't come with poison. What
poison? Back doors, kill switches and
and uh vasal hood. So we don't need that
poison. So I think you know if we get
the Suka 57 and we are able to modify it
if it comes under the under the proper
terms and conditions then we should be a
be able to improve it significantly. We
have tremendous electronics. We have a
tremendous radar that we manufacture
ourselves and we've got very frightening
missiles air-to-air missiles that we can
equip the the aircraft with. So if we
can modify the Suka 57 to our
requirements we can transform it into a
very dangerous beast. So I think makes
sense to go for it.
Okay. Now, okay. What is the question?
Saranga Ninal says, "Can you please shed
some light and brief on the stand of the
ASEAN nations on China, US India
dynamic? Why do they who who do the side
with? Could you give a detailed analysis
in one of your episodes? We'll see.
Maybe I can do that in the future." See,
the ASEAN nations, they don't want to be
part of any big fight. They want to be
left alone. They want to be they want to
just mind their own business. They want
to trade with other nations. They want
to grow their economies and provide
better living standards for other
nations. That's all they care about.
They are not interested in who's
fighting whom. They are scared of China.
They are scared of the US also. India
they're not scared of and they like
India. Uh so if they are given a choice,
they would actually prefer India or all
these nations. But you know China has
tremendously deep pockets and when
Xiinping comes visiting you, you treat
him with respect and you ask him to
invest and obviously he will invest. But
then he will also bully you at the same
time. So that's the problem with China.
So they would like to side with nobody.
But if effectively who do they side
with? They side with the US. They side
more with the US than with with anybody
else. But they are they have never been
against India and they're scared of
China. But they don't like the US also
because the US is a big bully and
everyone knows that. So that's the deal.
That's the dynamic. The friendliest they
are is towards India. The most amount of
goodwill they have towards a nation,
it's India.
But India has never really taken the
time to do a proper outreach and so on.
Until in recent times, even now, I think
we can do much better. We should have
people-to-people relations with with
Indonesia, with Thailand, with Cambodia,
with Vietnam. Right now, Thailand and
Cambodia are fighting each other for the
for the ancient Shiva temple, the Priya
Vihar temple. I think we should mediate.
We should mediate. Why not? Both will
trust us uh if unless we mess up and so
on. So yeah, that's that's the deal with
ASEAN.
Uh MK says, "How did the Soviets counter
the German blitzkrieak?" The Germans
could have won. The Soviets were losing.
They were giving up kilometer after
kilometer of the territory. Hundreds of
kilometers they gave up. More than a
thousand kilometers of of territory.
They gave up. Right. The German
Blitzkrieg was super successful.
Operation Barbar Roa. They punched all
the way deep into the Soviet lines. At
the end of the day, eventually they were
they were on the outskirts of Moscow.
They could see Moscow with with
binoculars. But what went wrong? A
decision, a choice they made. They said
that okay, let let let's wait for
Moscow. Let's go down south for the
Caucasus region where the big oil fields
are because Germany needs oil.
But that gave Moscow sufficient time to
somehow wait things out.
And then the great old
German, sorry, the great old Russian
general came into the battlefield,
General Winter. And General Winter
doesn't doesn't isn't isn't merciful. So
the price the Germans paid for the wrong
choice was that tens of thousands of
their soldiers just froze. Froze where
they were. They froze. They became
stone. Died.
And then the Russian counteroffensive
began. The Russians had did all they had
done all these horrible purges in the
1930s late 1930s 37 onwards. All their
great generals were killed off by Stalin
and Molotov.
I mean Switchin the great scholar
Switchin was killed and so on. So the
German the so the Russian
military was was essentially brand new.
All the great leaders had been killed
off because Stalin was suspicious of
them. So the Russians had to learn how
to fight. They had learn they had to
learn operational arts and strategy and
tactics and all all that on the go while
fighting on the job. But they somehow
managed
and once winter came in the the Soviets
came into their own and they started
pushing the Germans back inch by inch,
foot by foot, mile by mile until they
reached Berlin and they spent oceans of
blood to defeat the Germans. My god.
Nobody fought more than the Soviets.
Nobody bled more than the Soviets.
Nobody died more than Soviets. More than
20 27 million Russians died in this. But
they prevailed and they defeated the
Germans.
Okay.
Um
let's see what else do we have. Um,
Vishal says, "You said Starlink won't be
turned off when the Indian government
restricts internet in an area, but
during internet shutdown only mobile
sins are SIMs are turned off. Home Wi-Fi
is never shut off. It's always on. You
may have not lived in an area where some
such disturbances happened because when
the government wants to switch off the
internet, it actually switches off the
internet. your home Wi-Fi can be on but
there will be no signal
right so unless you receive signals
to your home from outside
you will not be able to use Wi-Fi
let's say you don't have a router but
you have a I mean you don't have the
modem
which which gets signals from outside
but you have a router Wi-Fi router at
home and you switch it on but it's not
connected to a modem then what the hell
will it do you will get a signal when
phone but that signal is like there's
nothing in it. So please understand the
nuances. I don't know why it's so hard
to understand but okay I'm happy to
answer the questions.
Okay
Senpai says India's growth projections
are based on its young population but as
AI improves and reduces the value of
human labor will our demographic
advantage diminish weakening India's
edge over other nations? It could it
could our demographic dividend etc etc
all the wonderful slogans that we have
they're based on the value of human
capital and human ne labor but if AI
becomes a big deal which it will I
promise it will
then and especially if you can when AI
becomes robotic robotics enabled or
robotics becomes AI enabled then you
will have factories that work 24/7 they
work in the dark they don't need lights
they keep on churning out goods
so if we can become an early adopter of
these technologies then our demographic
advantage may diminish but it won't
affect our economic output. It may
actually enhance our economic output. So
we have to play the game right. We
cannot be left behind in the EI and
robotics race. As long as we are among
the front runners of this we're going to
do well and the demographic advantage or
lack of it eventually will not make any
difference.
Nut
says why does India allow Turkish
companies in our sensitive avision
industry? I think we should not and why
does it do it? We I'm not the person to
ask this question. You have to ask the
government of India what on earth are
you people doing? What are you people
doing? Why are you allowing these
nations nations like Turkey into our
sensitive sectors? Why are you allowing
China to provide 80% of our of our CCTV
cameras?
These are all economic threats, security
threats, national security threats
and there are other nations that are
whose equipment is national security
threats and so on. So yeah, this is
something the government needs to answer
and they need to not just answer but
they need to do something about this.
Okay.
Mlevin says last month I asked you a
question about US setting camp in
Bangladesh and probably a deal on the
table cookie line in exchange of P can
you answer that now
you had answer asked this had I taken
this and refused to answer okay let's
answer the question anyway
US setting camp in Bangladesh
in a deal cook in exchange for P so
India gets k and India gives up half of
manipur and misoram
if the US gives us a deal like that. We
should laugh it off. We can tell them to
go tell them to go and go to hell.
If they want to do things in Bangladesh,
that's their prerogative because
Bangladesh is a separate nation. They
have taken it over. They need a coup and
they they have their own puppet
government there now just like in
Pakistan. So they have east and west
Pakistan. If they want to mess around
there, you do it. But the moment you try
try to touch Indian territory, we're
going to be there's going to be hell to
pay for that. So if the US gives such
such a deal, it puts a deal on the
table. You give us cookie land for
Christ and we we'll give you PK back, we
should tell them to take a hike.
I can think of very various impolite
things to say, but I'll not utter those
words here. But yeah, that's what we
should do.
Satur 88 says, can you explain the ornik
weapon develop weapon system developed
by Russia? How does the west look at it
and does India need such a weapon to
counter China? The ornik is some kind of
missile, right? I don't know the details
of the missile.
There's the which is obviously a stealth
fighter bomber kind of thing. The
Orishnik is some kind of missile
probably a hypersonic missile. Um
maybe it's a ballistic missile with a
hypersonic entry entry speed or
something and maybe intermediate range.
I'm not I don't remember exactly what it
is now. I could do a Google search but
but yeah so um I'm sure it's a good
missile pretty dangerous missile and
pretty scary missile uh how does the
west look at it I'm sure they look at it
with concern does India need weapons to
counter China we have our own weapons to
counter China and until recently we have
never seen Indian missiles in action but
now we know what they look like and what
they sound like they're pretty pretty
scary so I'm sure that the see the
missiles that we saw land in Pakistan
which were all the all those videos
filmed by Pakistanis right missiles
landing on Nurh Khan air base and saroda
and um Chakalala and Rahul Pindi and
wherever
we get we got to see what a missile
looks and sounds like when you know the
receiving end. Um so those missiles that
we saw were short distance cruise
missiles and short range ballistic
missiles most likely or or other kinds
of missiles uh surfaceto-air miss sorry
airto-surface missiles perhaps and and
drones. When it comes to China we need
intermediate to longrange missiles not
ICBMs but the intermediate range
missiles missiles with a with a range of
about 5,000 roughly kilometers. Yeah. So
once you have those then you can you
know make China behave and we have those
obviously I'm sure the AGN4 can take
care of uh
all of Chinese territory. The Agnifi can
go beyond that and we possibly have
certain other tools in our toolkit that
we don't speak about. And we also have
longd distance hypersonic missiles that
are going to be tested. Uh I'm talking
about hypersonic cruise missiles that
are going going to be tested with a
range of 1500 or so kilometers. The
bramos has extended ranges now that
could be in excess of 800 to,000 km
possibly uh and so on. So we have a
whole bunch of missiles ranging from
cruise missiles to ballistic missiles
and so on. And we don't need an
orishnik. We have our own very scary
weapons weapons.
So yeah, we when it comes to missiles,
we're good. We don't need anything from
anybody. We probably have the scariest
missiles in the world.
Uh
anonymous scientist says would it be
beneficial for India to restart
operation sindur in winter as as it
would keep the PLA at bay. We did
operation sindur in May in the height of
summer and the PLA stray away. Right.
The problem isn't China in this matter.
China could become a problem but the
problem is the US. The problem is Trump.
Okay.
So yeah, sure, restart operation Sindur
in winter, but Trump will again come in
the way and he'll impose sanctions this
time. Last time he threatened and so on.
Um
Amisha says, "Why don't we see stars
nowadays? How did the sky look like 100
years back?" Well, I wasn't there 100
days back, so I don't know what it looks
like. I don't have memories of that but
I was there in my childhood and the the
sky was very different back then. So
what do we have today? We have two major
problems in the sky today. One is
pollution.
So the entire sky is obscured with all
this dust and smoke all over the place
especially in metropolitan cities in
India. So there is that form of
pollution and then there is light
pollution. So what light pollution does
is that it augments the air pollution.
The smoke and the dust that that that
blankets a city like a miasma that is
now lit up with the light pollution. So
what that causes is this glowing
envelope of of of noxious gas over a
city. So when you look up you see the
whole sky is glowing orange or white or
whatever or a mixture and because of
that you hardly get to see stars except
for the brightest ones.
So that's the combination of light
pollution and air pollution. Let's say
you have no air pollution. You just have
light pollution. Even then you have this
big glow in the sky and that will you
know uh dim out the the stars.
Now if you go to a remote area let's say
you go to a forest or you go to a hilly
place where there's no big cities and
all that then you will see that at night
you can see all the stars and the stars
are super visible. You can even see the
Milky Way. One of my earliest memories
of my life is is seeing the Milky Way
and I was like what on earth is that?
This whole band of stars that look like
a cloud but it's actually stars and it's
part of the galaxy that we live in. So
30, 40 years ago, 50 years ago in India,
most cities were still very dark and you
could see all the stars and I remember
as a small kid, I used to sometimes uh
spend hours on the terrace of our house
and I used to look at the sky and I used
to wonder what's going on out there and
I you know I could I knew all the stars
essentially. I knew all of them
individually. I did not know the names
of all the stars but I knew them by the
way they looked and the colors and their
the the patterns you know the
constellation constellations and and so
on so forth and I used to sit and wonder
what's going on up there what's going on
who all who all is out there and so that
sort of thing so the reason we don't see
stars nowadays because of a combination
of of of
atmospheric pollution and light
pollution and a 100 years back the sky
looked beautiful you could see stars
recently Recently, I remember a few
years ago there was a big power blackout
in New York and the people started
calling the police because there was
there was saying strange stuff in the
sky that strange stuff was a Milky Way.
Uh
Chirasi says, "Why is it that China
always loses when a nation or an empire
does a brute force attack on them? Why
have they always lost despite having a
large population and resources?" Uh I
look every nation has its own character
has its own personality has its own way
of doing things and maybe there's
something about China that that causes
this issue. So
you know I did a podcast about 3 years
ago with Dr. Edward Lutwak one of my you
know when I was like 20 years younger I
was like who is this guy Edward Lutwak I
would he writes wonderful books about
geo strategy and history and then one
day I got to do a podcast with him in
which I spent an hour with him. Um I did
this podcast with him and he said that
he he cracked a joke. He's a very funny
guy. He cracked a joke. He says that you
know how do you conquer China? What do
you need? What does it take to conquer
China? And the answer is three guys on
horseback. That's it. So the moment you
take the war to China's homeland, the
Chinese lose. Every time somebody has
invaded them and forced them to fight on
their own territory, the Chinese have
lost. Historically you've seen this
pattern but when the Chinese fight
outside of their homeland beyond their
own territory they often win. Not always
but they sometime they often win. So
that's that's a key to understanding
China. We have we cannot forget that you
want to beat them you to beat them on
their territory.
Okay.
Bank says how does China feel about
Pakistan being cozy with the US and how
does the US feel about China being co
Pakistan being cozy with China both are
fine with it they understand look these
nations are not emotional like us we are
like oh you backstabbed me you were
working with me and now you're in bed
with the other guy that sort of thing
these nations understand how things work
um Pakistan wants as many masters as
possible to have as many benefits as
possible and The US and China see eye to
eye on them on the question of India.
They both want Pakistan as a as a big
counterbalance to India. So China and
the US are okay. Of course the US
doesn't want Pakistan to become too
closely attached to China. That's why
they have taken steps and measures and
the Pakistanis themselves are more
comfortable with the US than with China.
So that is the the dynamic
between these nations.
Okay. Gal says striking demona with
standoff beyond visual range weapons
requires serious ISR Chinese ISR
any evidence or indications any oent
material
related to that defect the Iranians have
tremendous
tremendously good
um
missiles ballistic and cruise missiles
they also have drones
that which they're able to launch
at Israel. They have done that in the
past. A few months ago, there were these
attacks, right? The tit tit for tat
attacks. Um, so the Iranians have very
high quality missiles, ballistic
missiles. They have hypersonic missiles,
maybe cruise missiles or whatever that
is, and they have high quality drones.
So you launch all of this in
coordination, it can overwhelm the local
air defenses, the iron dr dome or
whatever it is. So yeah, that that's
what the Iranians are capable of.
Um,
okay. Let's take a couple more
questions. After that, we are done.
We'll be done after that until tomorrow.
Um,
Bishop says read regarding reading
bombing atomic weapons on Japan. Was it
necessary even to some extent? If yes,
then why twice? They were very cruel.
They exploited our people in Anaman
Island. The Japanese military during the
Second World War was very cruel. Okay, I
agree. No question. Okay. Why were they
cruel? Because they had given up. They
had given up dharma.
And as long as the Maji Empire as as as
the as the samurai existed, the Japanese
nation was founded on the principles of
dharma, the dharmic principles. But the
Maji restoration attempted to uproot
dharma out of Japan. as a consequence it
was able to adherify their their
military and that's why it did such
horrible things to to the people they
conquered. Yeah. Very very very cruel
stuff. Now was it necessary to bomb
Japan with atomic weapons? I think it
was a test to see the effect of atomic
weapons on human beings. And of course
the justification was that otherwise an
invasion of Japan would have cost
hundreds of thousands of American lives.
And by and by bombing them we were we
were able to make them su to make them
surrender and so on. And because we
bombed them once and they did not
surrender we had to bomb them twice. So
that's the thing and that's how it goes.
Overall these were atomic tests on human
beings and they lo they caused a
tremendous amount of suffering among
civilians.
Okay.
Abijit cha light says how can UFOs fly
without propulsion systems? Do we have
UFOs exist? Do we have evidence that UFO
exists? That UFOs exist? Well, I've
never seen a UFO.
Have I? Maybe not. Maybe. So, look,
first of all, we don't know these UFOs
exist. And secondly, how do we know that
if they exist, they fly without
propulsion technology or systems? Maybe
they have they have some systems. Maybe
the UFOs are Loheed Martin technology or
maybe they are ISRO technology or
something technology you know advanced
technology that nobody knows about. If
they are flying it means they have some
kind of system that is propelling them.
Um
Mayang says is Indian missile problem on
par with US, China, Russia? Considering
we will have functional hyper hyperbolic
hypersonic missile soon and US doesn't
have it. It's possible that our missile
system is probably more advanced than
most nations in the world. At least in
terms of missiles, we are behind nobody.
We are at least on par with the top
nations in the world. on par for sure if
not ahead of them. So yeah, we will soon
have functioning hypersonic missiles.
There's there's an upcoming hypersonic
test which will happen anytime soon of a
missile with a 1500 km range with a
hypersonic motor. So that'll be fun. So
I think when it comes to missiles, we
are we are behind nobody at all in the
world.
And uh with that I think we come to the
end of today's session. So thank you
very much for the questions. Um and I'll
see you tomorrow in tomorrow's live
stream. I'll decide tomorrow whether to
turn super chat back on again or not.
Perhaps super chat is more simp is
probably simpler for me. But let's see
about that. So tomorrow we have an
episode of the Indian interest at 8:00
p.m. India time. After that, once that
ends, I'll immediately go into another
episode of the Ask Abig show. So, I hope
to see you then tomorrow, 8:00 p.m.
Until then, take care, keep asking
questions, keep raising your standards,
and I'll see you tomorrow. Thank you.
Bye-bye.